A Guide to the Papers of the Shackelford Family, 1911-1919, 1943-1945.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Shackelford Family, 1911-1919, 1943-1945.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3525-m, 3525-aa, 6558
This collection consists of 105 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Shackelford Family Papers were made a gift to the University on November 20, 1980.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains World War I and II correspondence of members of the Shackelford family. Topics include military training and the war in France, 1917-1918; employment with the United States Shipping Board Emergency Fleet Corporation's Legal Division; SHAEF messages from Eisenhower re the surrender of Germany, 1945 May 7; tours of duty in Hawaii, Okinawa, and China during and after World War II, 1943-1946, particularly air raids, victory celebrations, fighting on Okinawa, U. S. forces in China at the close of the war, Chinese nationalists and the Communist revolution; as well as the formation of the Monticello Graveyard Association and a proposed armory on University of Virginia grounds.
Contents List
- Accession #3525-m
  - Letters from George Scott Shackelford, Jr. to Mr. and Mrs. George Scott Shackelford 1918, 4 items
    Letters re: GSS's training in a cavalry military school in France, censorship of outgoing mail,etc. during WWI.
  - Letters from R. Gascoigne Lyne to Virginius Randolph and Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford 1917-1918, 9 items
    Letters re: RGL's military schooling in France, and his work on the Front during WWI. Includes one letter to his parents.
    - Re: Legion of Honor awards ceremony for French soldiers. 10 Feb 1918
    - Re: a spring offensive planned against Germany by the Allies 25 Aug 1918
    - Re: an airplane battle between [Allied] and German flyers 25 Sep 1918
    - Re: German brutalities to French children and to the Allies; pet names given to their guns by the Allied soldiers 18 Oct 1918
    - News clipping re: RGL n.d.
  - Letters from George Scott Shackelford, Jr. to Virginius Randolph and Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford 1917-1919, 9 items
    Letters re: GSS's training at a military cavalry school in France during WWI.
    - Re: air and ground battles between Allied and German Forces; GSS's work in the medical corps with the French; encounters with French prostitutes. 19 Jan 1917
  - Business Letters to Virginius Randolph Shackelford 1911-1918, 15 items
    Includes four letters (May 1913) re: formation of the Monticello Graveyard Association at the University. Jefferson Randolph Kean was president of the MGA.
    - Letter of Jefferson Randolph Kean re: his work in France in the American Expeditionary Forces during WWI 26 Feb 1918
    - Re: VRS's employment in the Legal Division of the United States Shipping Board Emergency Fleet Corporation. Jun - Dec 1918
  - United States Shipping Board 1917-1918, 12 items
    Printed material re: the United States Shipping Board Emergency Fleet Corporation, where Virginius Randolph Shackelford was employed. Charles M. Schwab was Director-General.
  - Correspondence to Jefferson Randolph Kean 1918, 3 items
    - Re: promotion of George [Scott] Shackelford, Jr. 11 Mar 1918
    - News clipping re: JRK. n.d.
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1918, n.d., 12 items
    Printed material re: Red Cross activities and a patriotic festival in Orange, Virginia. Includes copies of speeches delivered.
  - Newsclipping re: Virginius Randolph Shackelford n.d.
- Accession #3525-aa
  - World War II SHAEF Messages 7 May 1945, 2 items
    Re: the surrender of Germany in WWII. Reads in part, "A representative of the German High Command signed the unconditional surrender...," "signed Eisenhower."
- Accession #6558
  - World War II Letters from George Green Shackelford to Virginius Randolph and Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford 1943-1946, 3 folders. 38 items.
    Letters re: GGS's tours of duty in California, Hawaii, and China during WWII; mention of many University of Virginia graduates, and friends and relatives in Orange, Virginia.
  - Folder 1 1943-1945
    - re: a code set up by GGS to by-pass Navy censors. [1 Dec 1944]
    - 7 May 1945
      Re: rewiring, making safe, and pludering a mine-filled cave in Okinawa.
    - Re: Japanese suicide attacks and air raids on Okinawa; news of several of GGS's friends; mention of an "inside story" about Patton and MacArthur. 3 Jun 1945
    - Re: Patton, MacArthur, and problems in the Army 6 Jun 1945
  - Folder 2: 1945
    - Re: Gov. Darden's efforts to build an armory on U.Va. grounds; a postscript (5 Aug 1945) re: an evening with Charles Jennings Randolph, Jr., of the Thomas Mann Randolph family. 2 Aug 1945
    - 10 Aug 1945
      Re: "the prospects for V-J" [victory over Japan]; loss of the [U.S.S.] Underhill.
    - Re: victory and peace celebrations in the Navy 18 Aug 1945
    - Includes printed material from St. Andrew's Parish in Honolulu 23 Aug 1945
    - Re: some opposition by Admirals Halsey and Nimitz to MacArthur in Japan. 29 Aug [1945]
    - Letter and printed material of Geo[rge] O. Ferguson, re: courses at U.Va. 5 Sep 1945
    - Re: lifting of censorship of outgoing mail; details about ships on which GGS sailed, including duties, privileges, characteristics of the ships; sailing to China, passengers on board, the Chinese revolution. 2 Nov 1945
    - Re: GGS's arrival in Shanghai, China; a typhoon in Shanghai, life on the Yangtze River in the boat villages, U.S. forces in China, shore leave in [Shanghai], the new Communist government, the Communist revolution and its Soviet backing, re: the 1945 Communist takeover, "what is happening here will have great significance and importance..." 8 Nov 1945
    - Re: GGS's activities in China; communism in China. 29 Nov 1945
  - Folder 3: 1945-1946
    - Re: establishing the U.S. naval base in Tangku, China; Navy equipement, Chinese Nationalists, conduct of Navy enlisted men. 2 Dec 1945
    - Re: furlough in Peiping, "the city is still in the fourteenth century," as U.S. and Chinese Nationalists fight communism; siteseeing in China, nightclubs, temples, the Forbidden City, travel on the only open rail line, etc. 9 Dec 1945
    - Re: a visit by the Generalissimo [Chiang Kai Shek?] to GGS's naval base in China. 31 Jan 1946
    - News clipping re: the [U.S.S.] Underhill. n.d.